Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is קכ"ד, Kuf Chaf
Daled, 124. We pick up at the bottom of קכ"ג עמוד ב.
Kuf Chaf Gimmel Amud Bet. We're in the middle of talking about
מוקצה, muktzeh, specifically about כלים, keilim, about vessels that are normally used
and aren't מוקצה. muktzeh. But there was this thing called גזירת כלים
gezeirat keilim in the time of נחמיה Nechemiah because of the rampant
חילול שבת, chilul Shabbat, so they said don't use any vessels at
all except maybe some very very basic ones and then slowly there
was a pushback and there was slowly more and more things were
allowed. And now the only issues remain amongst things that are like
never moved because they're like special professional
vessels or things that are used for איסור, issur, כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור,
kli shemelachto l'issur, which is not real מוקצה muktzeh again, it's amongst
your vessels, it's amongst things that normally are used, but there's limits
you cannot move that for certain purposes. You can't move it for
to protect it חמה לצל chamah l'tzel or there's actually a debate
of the אמוראים, Amoraim, but that's רבא's Rava position and that's the
way we rule. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up four lines
from the bottom on קכ"ג עמוד ב. Kuf Chaf Gimmel Amud Bet.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, said רבי אלעזר: Rabbi Elazar:
קנים ומקלות, kanim u-maklot, גלוסטרא ומדוכה, glustra u-maducha,
sticks or like reeds, rods,
a like גלוסטרא glustra which is like a knob at the top
of a bolt and the מדוכה, maducha, the pestle, the mortar and
pestle or the mortar I should say. כולן קודם לגזירת כלים נשנו.
Kulan kodem l'gezeirat keilim nishnu. All of these are משניות mishnayot or
that are extremely restrictive about the use of vessels on שבת Shabbat
and all of them were from the ancient period when like almost
all vessels were forbidden. So let's take a look. So this is
his way of explaining four משניות mishnayot that are very restrictive. Let's
take a look.
You're also saying things that we don't abide by.
We don't abide by these משניות, mishnayot, correct. You're dismissing them. Correct,
correct, exactly.
So רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar taking a historical approach to תורה שבעל
פה.
Torah
she-be-al peh. Right, exactly. Framing... well, no, the גמרא Gemara does sometimes
like this גמרא Gemara that says that there was an early תקנה
takanah and then they pushed it back, or sometimes the גמרא Gemara
says, you know, sometimes it's even in the משנה. Mishnah. משנה ראשונה,
Mishnah rishonah, the original teaching was this. משנה אחרונה אמרו Mishnah achronah
amru and then they and then the later teaching was the following
and it rejected משנה ראשונה Mishnah rishonah and then sometimes the גמרא
Gemara will say that certain lines in certain משניות mishnayot are from
the earlier teachings and are no longer the הלכה. halacha. So the
גמרא Gemara does sometimes put a historical framework on these even for
the import of explaining that whether they are continued to be relevant
or not. So that's a very good point
that both Rifka and Charlie are making and that is being said
here. So let's take a look at these משניות. mishnayot. דתנן, Ditnan,
we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: לא סידור הקנים ולא נטילתן דוחה
את השבת. lo sidur hakanim v'lo netilatan docheh et hashabbat.
Neither the placing of the reeds or the removing of them overrides
שבת. Shabbat. Thank you very much. This is about the לחם הפנים,
lechem hapanim, right, which is like I think why they picked this
picture in the well in the what do you call it in
for the cover of Steinsaltz there. They would put on the new
bread on שבת Shabbat and remove the old bread. Now the breads
were stacked in two columns of six loaves each and each loaf
was separated from the other one with these like reeds that helped
to suspend it, basically made a shelf
of like three reeds, air space got in, but a shelf that
separated each loaf from the bottom one. And you know you had
the vertical columns and the reeds were sort of like you put
a shelf in your bookshelf but except these were like reeds that
had air between them but they created this shelf that you put
the bread on that kept the bread separate. So
you would not, when you were coming to remove the bread and
put on the new ones, you would not put the new reeds
up, you would not take off the reeds or put them up,
neither of that would be דוחה השבת docheh hashabbat or override שבת.
Shabbat. Now, so he says what's the reason for that? The reeds
should be totally usable. It's כלי שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto l'heter. So
obviously this is before they allowed any כלים keilim and this was
when even the most trivial of כלים keilim were not allowed to
be used.
You could even have been thinking that
it's כלים keilim
is an ur-גזירה gezerah like you know...
Yeah it's true you could argue that it's not כלים keilim and
it's alright so same point.
Anyway so there's a rabbinic prohibition in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash
which is...
yeah well right so that's an issue. So first of all, first
of all you could have said that maybe the problem was maybe
it was more a little bit like עשיית כלי asiyat kli or
something like that, you know who said it was a מוקצה muktzeh
type of a concern?
So that's number one. Number two is whatever happened to the prohibition
that we don't make דרבננס d'rabbanans in the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash?
So you look at תוספות: Tosafot: לא סידור קנים אף אגב דאין
שבות במקדש כמה שבות משכח במקדש. lo sidur kanim af agav d'ein
shevut b'mikdash kamma shevut mashkach b'mikdash. Alright, it's not an absolute rule
even though generally there are דרבננס, d'rabbanans, some are okay and maybe
specifically at this time when they forbade all vessels maybe because to
push because there was so much rampant חילול שבת chilul Shabbat maybe
they restrict on it in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash as well.
Okay
so רש"י Rashi says that what they would do therefore because you
should say look, if you're not removing the old reeds then what's
the issue, you don't have to put up new
ones, but רש"י Rashi says no they would
remove. Again, these are sort of serving like shelves and then they
would take off the bread on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbat*, put on the
new bread on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, and then מוצאי שבת Shabbos *Motzei
Shabbat* they would put in the reeds again to separate the bread.
So what's the big concern with these reeds? It must be this
was the time when almost all vessels were forbidden. Then it says
מקלות maklos *Maklos*, what is the story about the about the bars?
You know like the poles? דתנן d'tnan *De-nan*, we taught in the
משנה mishna. *Mishna* in פסחים *Psachim*. מקלות דקים חלקים היו שם *Maklos
dakim chalakim hayu sham*, that there were thin smooth poles there in
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* for the purposes of קרבן פסח Pesach.
*Korban Pesach*. ומניח על כתיפו ועל כתיף חברו *U-maniach al kteifo ve-al
kteif chaveiro*, and when you were coming to flay the קרבן פסח
Pesach, *Korban Pesach*, you would basically because again, this was not like
the כהנים *Kohanim* were flaying like they would do by normal קרבנות
*Korbanot*, here every single person or every little group of people had
their own קרבן *Korban* and the whole thing was like, you know,
hundreds of thousands of people, so it was sort of a little
do-it-yourself. So each person would take a pole and suspend it from
his shoulder and his friend's shoulder, ותולה *ve-toleh*, and suspend the קרבן
פסח *Korban Pesach* from it, ומפשיט *u-mafshit*, and flay the קרבן *Korban*.
אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Elazar* or רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer
omer, *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, ארבעה עשר שחל להיות בשבת b'Shabbat. *arba'ah asar
she-chal lihyot be-Shabbat*, this also is very nice. But when ערב פסח
erev Pesach. *Erev Pesach* fell out on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, right, so
then you obviously could bring the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach* on שבת
Shabbos *Shabbat*, but you were limited in terms of what you could
do, and you might remember, you know, there's, well anyway, so there's
a question in general, right, about flaying it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*,
maybe that's needed because of preventing the meat from spoiling, some of
those issues were touched on earlier. Anyway, he's concerned here about the
use of these rods. So he said if it was שבת Shabbos?
*Shabbat*, then מניח ידו על כתיף חברו ויד חברו על כתיפו *maniach
yado al kteif chaveiro ve-yad chaveiro al kteifo*, then you don't use
the rod, you just use your own arms to do it, you
know, you put your arm on his shoulder, his shoulder on your
arm, ותולה ומפשיט *ve-toleh u-mafshit*, you suspend it from your arms. I
hope you have a pretty messy and I hope you have a
third person because if you're using your arms to suspend, your ability
to be ומפשיט *u-mafshit*, anyway. But the point is, what's the big
deal with these rods? Right? I mean now maybe you'll say okay,
it's a כלי kli... שמלאכטו לאיסור *kli she-melachto le-issur*, but still it's
לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo, *le-tzorech gufo*, so what's the whole problem here?
So again, this was at a period when almost all כלים keilim
*kelim* were forbidden. This is a holdover from the time of נחמיה
Nechemya, *Nechemya* when almost all כלים keilim, *kelim* were forbidden. Okay, number
three, גלוסטרא glustra, *glustra*, a like a bolt with a knob at
the top. דתנן *De-nan*, we taught in the משנה mishna. *Mishna*, נגר
שיש בראשו גלוסטרא *nagar she-yesh be-rosho glustra*, if you have a door
bolt essentially that has a bulb at the top. רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer שומטו מן הפתח זה ותולה בחברו בשבת *Rabbi Yehuda
omer shomto min ha-petach zeh ve-toleh be-chaveiro be-Shabbat*, that you basically can
remove it from one door and put it in another door, apparently
this was a bolt that you could put, you know, through the
like whatever, you know, the rings that they had that you would
bolt a door against the frame with. So you could remove it
from one and put it in the other. רבי דוסא אומר הרי
הוא ככל הכלים ומטלטל בחצר *Rabbi Dosa omer harei hu ke-chol ha-kelim
u-mitaltel be-chatzer*, it's like all vessels and you can move it in
the courtyard. So what's going on here?
So this is a case where you need it לצורך גופו l'tzorech
gufo, *le-tzorech gufo*, also it seems to be a כלי kli שמלאכטו
להיתר *kli she-melachto le-heter*, right? There's no problem. So nevertheless, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* understands that when רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua* says
שומטו *shomta*, you can like sort of slip it off, that the
basic point is that it doesn't mean it means somehow you can't
move it directly. You can maybe like drag it from one door
to the other, that's how the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is understanding the
phrase of
שומטו *shomta*, and not directly move it even though it's מלאכתו להיתר
melachto l'heter, *melachto le-heter*. And it's only what's his name, it's only
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon's *Rabbi Tarfon* who says that no, no, no,
it can totally be handled normally. Now it's a little bit hard,
one minute, it's a little hard to say that this is from
the period before כלים *kelim* were permissible because first of all you
have רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* that allows it, and number two, רבי
טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* says הרי הוא ככל הכלים *harei hu ke-chol ha-kelim*,
right, that this is like all other vessels, which means that all
other vessels are allowed. So it's a little bit unclear what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* means by saying this was before התרת כלים hataras
keilim, *hatarat kelim*, but maybe it means that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
*Rabbi Yehoshua*'s teaching was a holdover, which would be even more interesting.
It wasn't just like the משנה Mishna, *Mishna* was an old משנה
Mishna, *Mishna*, you know, it's that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*
was teaching and his tradition was a holdover from an earlier period
and רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon* is coming to correct that. Okay, but
that's how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is framing it. The last one,
מדוכה meducha *maducha*, and the case of the mortar. הא דאמרן *Ha
de-aman*, like we said, the case of the mortar with the clove
of garlic, that it said you could only move it with the
garlic. Why is that? Even if it's a כלי kli שמלאכטו לאיסור
*kli she-melachto le-issur*, you should be able to move it for its
own purpose. So all of these seem to be very restrictive and
the explanation is they're a holdover from the old time. So אמר
רבא amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, said רבא Rava, *Rava*, ממאי mimai *mi-mai*,
who told you that that's the way to explain all these משניות
mishnayos *mishnayot*? דילמא dilma לעולם *Dilma le-olam*, I'll tell you, אחר התרת
כלים נשנו *achar hatarat kelim nishnu*, this was after basically the vessels
were made permissible, with, you know, limits of כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli
shemelachto l'issur. *kli she-melachto le-issur*. And here's the reason though why you
have the limits in these משניות mishnayos *mishnayot*. קנים *Kanim*, the case
of the reeds that separate the לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim*, טעמא מאי
*ta'ama mai*, what's the reason? משום עבושי *mishum ivushai*, because you why
do you in general separate the loaves of bread with these reeds?
Because you're afraid it'll get moldy. והאי פורתא *Ve-hai purta*, this little
time, it's
actually
not so little stays for like whatever twelve hours or however long
it is and then the new bread stays for twelve hours, but
all the loaves only stay without separation for half a day. So
that little amount of time לא lo מעפש won't get moldy, so
there's no need to allow it. Now the impetus, well let me
read the other one, מקלות the poles, אפשר כרבי אלעזר, efshar k'Rabbi
Elazar, you could do like with your arms. Now this is very
strange. He says okay, it could be that we're talking nowadays when
things are actually allowed, but the reason we're restrictive here is there
are other ways of doing it. It's not such a demand,
it's not so needed to separate them with the reeds, it's not
so needed to use the poles. Now the point is, as Michael
says, so what? If it's כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli she-melachto l'heter, certainly
the reeds are כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli she-melachto l'heter, the pole you
could say is אסור assur because it's של פסיפס. shel pesifas. But
if the reeds are כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli she-melachto l'heter, so who
cares if there's not so much of a need? If כלי שמלאכתו
להיתר kli she-melachto l'heter is מותר, muttar, then it should be מותר
muttar period. This leads some פוסקים poskim to think
or to say that even when כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli she-melachto l'heter
is permissible, it's only permissible for a purpose,
meaning like לצורך גופו, l'tzorech gufo that you really somehow need it.
But if you don't really need it, then you can't even use
a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli she-melachto l'heter, which means like if I'm
taking I don't know,
what would be an example? My fork, or some say forks were
never in the גזירה gezeira at all, but what would be something?
I don't know what... Yeah because they always allowed you to use...
well every fork is a little different... because they didn't have forks
at the time... anyway, but no no no, I'm saying those things,
if you remember, were never אסור. assur. But things that normally would
be אסור, assur, what would be an example of a כלי... kli
I don't know, a box, I take a little bit of a,
I just take a little box and I'm not doing anything with
it, I'm just playing with it, I'm just like my hands are
busy and I'm just playing with it. Some people say that's אסור
assur because even a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli she-melachto l'heter is only
allowed for if you're using it for a purpose. It's even after
התרת כלים, it's only allowed לצורך, l'tzorech, it's not סתם stam allowed.
Okay, that's not generally how people act and assume in terms of
these types of things, but some of that is like a little
bit learned, some want to learn that from this גמרא Gemara that
even when it deals with the reeds, it says if there's not
a real need, then maybe it's still אסור.
assur. No, but there is a need, even if it's not an
absolute necessity, it's a difference. You still can use it, meaning and
it will serve a constructive purpose...
Right, I mean that's what's funny about the reeds. The reeds actually
there is a purpose, you're just saying it's not like a very
as you say necessity or a strong need and even that seems
to be that that's an issue. So that is pretty so that
is pretty interesting in terms of suggesting that even כלי שמלאכתו להיתר
kli she-melachto l'heter you need a certain threshold to allow you to
use. That it's not the general way in which we practice and
which we assume, we assume כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli she-melachto l'heter is
across the board allowed, but there are some that actually do say
that.
As I said based on the implications of this גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
so that's the reeds and the poles. And then it says גלוסטרא,
this issue about the door bolt, כדבי ינאי k'debei Yanai like Yanai.
דאמר רבי ינאי, d'amar Rabbi Yanai, בחצר שאינה מעורבת עסקינן. bechatzer she-eina
meureves askinan. The problem of the door bolt is not a מוקצה
muktzah problem. The problem of the door bolt is is that the
door bolt is on the outside of the door, it's in the
door frame between the door and the door frame, it's on the
outside of the door and the courtyard doesn't have an עירוב. eruv.
So if the courtyard doesn't have an עירוב, eruv, you're not allowed
to move from the house into the courtyard. Okay, even though it's
got walls or whatever, if you haven't made this עירוב eruv that
everybody joining together right with food, then the courtyard is considered a
different domain than the house. So here's the concern, it has nothing
to do with
טלטול. tiltul. רבי יהושע סבר Rabbi Yehoshua savar תוף הפתח כדלפנים דמי.
tof hapetach k'dilifnim dami. Rabbi Yehoshua holds that in the door frame
is like considered inside the house. So if you were to move
it, remember רבי טרפון's phrase was כל הכלים
המטלטלין בחצר, kol hakeilim hamitaltelin bechatzer, it says it can be moved
in the חצר. chatzer. So that's what we're emphasizing because everybody agrees
you can move it. Question is can you bring it from the
door frame into the חצר? chatzer? So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says
no, it's considered to be in the door frame is in the
house. ומטלטל ממנא דבתים
בחצר. u'mitaltel mimana d'batim bechatzer.
And if you were to move it into straight away from one
house to another, from one door to another, you'd be moving it
from the house into the courtyard and that's a problem. So therefore
the only way you're allowed to do it is dragging it, somehow
dragging it makes it better, not exactly clear why.
That's his position. ורבי טרפון סבר v'Rabbi Tarfon savar תוף הפתח כדלחוץ
דמי. tof hapetach k'dilachutz dami. No, in the door frame it's like
it's in the courtyard already. And in the courtyard it can be
carried from one place in the courtyard to another place in the
courtyard. ומנא דחצר בחצר קמטלטל. u'mana d'chatzer bechatzer kamitaltel.
And you could move something in the חצר chatzer in the חצר.
chatzer. So you can move it from one door frame to the
other because it's all within the חצר. chatzer.
Yeah but he's saying כל הכלים kol hakeilim so that's a necessity.
Right so the point would be כל הכלים kol hakeilim that are
in the courtyard. I know, I understand. Okay מדוכה Meducha, and the
case about the mortar, ר' נחמיה היא. Rebbe Nechemia hi. That's Reb
Nechemia which we are finally going to see in the next משנה.
mishna That's always the answer we have in our back pocket that
another way of explaining restrictive משניות is by מוקצה. muktzah. is רבי
נחמיה Reb Nechemya's position that says you can only move things for
their designated purpose. So basically we have a range of restrictive משניות
by מוקצה. muktzeh. How do we explain them? One explanation is that
it's in this period of קודם גזירת הכלים. Kodem Gzeiras HaKeilim. The
other explanation is that it's רבי נחמיה Reb Nechemya who is very
restrictive. Okay,
and that was a similar answer that we used yesterday to say
that something was like רבי... רבי נחמיה. Rebby... Rebby Nechemya. A third
possibility that sometimes is relevant that the גמרא Gemara, said yesterday is
a type of a כלי kli that is so like a professional
כלי kli and something you don't want to use for another way
that it really is מוקצה muktzeh that's totally off-limits. But that's... but
the two that are sort of within the discussion of כלים and
not full מוקצה muktzeh is רבי נחמיה Reb Nechemya who is very
restrictive and this period of the time of נחמיה, the time of
the beginning of the בית ראשון... שני, Bayis Rishon... Sheini, which we
say was a holdover. Okay, and again the interesting thing is the
suggestion in the גמרא Gemara, above that even if we allow כלי
שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter completely, maybe not completely, maybe you need
some justifying purpose. But again, I... it's rare to find people that
are concerned about that, but that is an approach that some פוסקים
poskim have. Okay, let's take a look at the next משנה. כל
הכלים ניטלין לצורך ושלא לצורך. Kol hakeilim nitlin l'tzorech v'shelo l'tzorech. Again,
similar to the כל הכלים kol hakeilim from the opening of our...
of our פרק. perek. All vessels that you can move. Again, is
it מלאכתו להיתר, מלאכתו לאיסור, melachto l'heter, melachto l'issur, maybe both? You
can move for purpose and without a purpose. רבי נחמיה אומר אין
ניטלין
אלא לצורך. Reb Nechemya omer ein nitlin ela l'tzorech. They can only
be moved for a purpose. And now the... as we've been seeing
before, purpose is understood by the גמרא Gemara to mean for its...
for its designated purpose. You can only use a vessel for the
standard thing it's used for. Even a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli shemelachto
l'heter,
you can only use for the thing that it is generally used
for, which means you can't use a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto
l'issur, So if you can only use something for its designated purpose,
then you can use your fork as a fork and you can
use your box as a box, but you can't use a כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור, kli shemelachto l'issur a hammer, because that's only can be
used for its designated purpose, which you can't do on שבת. Shabbos
So that's רבי נחמיה. Reb Nechemya. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara מאי
לצורך ומאי שלא לצורך? Mai l'tzorech u'mai shelo l'tzorech? What does it
mean whether for its... whether for need or not need? So אמר
רבא, Rava. and this is going to be a little bit of
a recap of what we said yesterday.
לצורך, L'tzorech, for a need, דבר שמלאכתו להיתר לצורך גופו, davar shemelachto
l'heter l'tzorech gufo, meaning that you can use a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר
kli shemelachto l'heter for its own purpose. You can use a box
for a box. שלא לצורך, Shelo l'tzorech, not for a need, דבר
שמלאכתו להיתר לצורך מקומו, davar shemelachto l'heter l'tzorech mekomo, to get it
off the table if it's in your way. Okay, but what remains
forbidden is, this is the more restrictive approach, the approach of אביי
Abaye that we saw yesterday, that even a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli
shemelachto l'heter you cannot move to protect it. ודבר שמלאכתו לאיסור לצורך
גופו אין, לצורך מקומו לא. V'davar shemelachto l'issur l'tzorech gufo in, l'tzorech
mekomo lo. And something that's מלאכתו לאיסור melachto l'issur is one degree
more restrictive. You can only use it for its own purpose, like
a hammer to crack nuts, not to get it off the table.
ואתא רבי נחמיה למימר Va'ata Reb Nechemya l'meimar and comes רבי נחמיה
Reb Nechemya and says, אפילו דבר שמלאכתו להיתר, afilu davar shemelachto l'heter,
even something that is normally for היתר, heter, לצורך גופו אין, l'tzorech
gufo in, you can only move it לצורך גופו, l'tzorech gufo לצורך
מקומו לא, l'tzorech mekomo lo, you cannot move it just to get
it off the table. So that's the approach of אביי Abaye that
we saw yesterday, here attributed to רבא, Rava some actually have the
גירסא girsa here of אביי, Abaye, which basically says that even a
כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter cannot be moved to protect it.
Everything is one less than we normally practice. We practice כלי שמלאכתו
להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter can be used for all things, even to
protect it, and a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur can be
moved for לצורך גופו ומקומו, l'tzorech gufo and mekomo, but not to
protect it. He says one less in each category. כלי שמלאכתו להיתר
Kli shemelachto l'heter can be moved for its own purpose or to
get it off the table, but not to protect it, and כלי
שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur. only for its own purpose. Okay, so
that's more restrictive, we don't rule that way, but one level more
restrictive in each category. ורבי נחמיה אומר, V'Reb Nechemya omer, and רבי
נחמיה Reb Nechemya says you can only move anything, even מלאכתו להיתר,
melachto l'heter only for its own purpose. Yes?
What if it's in the way? Like oh, you left a hammer
on the table and you didn't realize or something and then you
and it was in the way.
So that's לצורך מקומו, l'tzorech mekomo, that's what we're talking about. Okay,
so according to the approach of אביי, Abaye, it would be permissible
to remove something that's מלאכתו להיתר melachto l'heter off the table, but
not the hammer. Now we don't rule that way. We להלכה l'halacha
you can even move the hammer off the table. Okay, so אביי
Abaye though was one degree more restrictive in each category. All right,
and he says if you've got your box out in the jewelry
box out in the yard and it's raining, you can't move it
to protect it. He's one degree more restrictive in each category. We
don't rule that way, that's what we're going to see רבא. Rava
אמר ליה רבא, So amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said to
him, לצורך מקומו שלא לצורך הוא, l'tzorech mekomo shelo l'tzorech hui, similar
to what he said yesterday. He basically thinks that anything you're moving
it because you need its space, that's considered an equal degree of
לצורך tzorech that you want to use it. Funny that assumption and
what's behind that assumption, but that's what he says. I don't understand
distinguishing between using it and getting it off the table. אלא אמר
רבא, Ela amar Rava, so rather רבא Rava. says, and this is
the way we rule, לצורך, l'tzorech, you can move something for a
need, דבר שמלאכתו להיתר בין לצורך גופו בין לצורך מקומו. davar shemelachto
l'heter bein l'tzorech gufo bein l'tzorech mekomo. You can move your jewelry
box whether you want to use it or whether you want it
off the table. ושלא לצורך, U'shelo l'tzorech, and that's considered לצורך. l'tzorech.
To use it or to get it off the table, equal degree
of need.
שלא לצורך, Shelo l'tzorech, you can even move it שלא לצורך, shelo
l'tzorech, which means what? ואפילו מחמה לצל, Va'afilu mechama l'tzel, even get
it out of the yard and stop the rain from falling on
it or getting warped. That, דבר שמלאכתו להיתר, davar shemelachto l'heter, you
can move for any purpose. ודבר שמלאכתו לאיסור V'davar shemelachto l'issur Something
like the hammer, לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו אין, l'tzorech gufo v'l'tzorech mekomo
in, yes you can use it to crack nuts, yes you can
move it to get it off the table, לצורך מקומו, l'tzorech mekomo,
so that's he again רבא Rava equates those two, cracking nuts, getting
off the table, those are equal. That you can move the hammer.
However, מחמה לצל אין, mechama l'tzel in, that you can, מחמה לצל
לא, mechama l'tzel lo, but you cannot move it out of the
courtyard to protect it from getting
warped, to bring it into the shade. So that's the way we
rule. We rule like רבא. Rava ואתא רבי נחמיה למימר v'ata Rebbe
Nechemiah l'meimar and then רבא Rava, says, then רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah
comes and says, ואפילו דבר שמלאכתו להיתר v'afilu davar she'melachto l'heter even
when you've got your jewelry box, לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו אין, l'tzorech
gufo v'l'tzorech mekomo in, that can only be moved, again, he equates
גופו gufo and מקומו, mekomo, only can be moved for its own
purpose and for its place, but מחמה לצל לא mechama l'tzel lo
cannot be moved to protect it. So again, רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah
is even, is more restrictive. So there's two issues going on. Number
one is what do we think the general פסק psak is? רבא
Rava is more lenient, the way we rule, מלאכתו להיתר melachto l'heter,
everything, מלאכתו לאיסור melachto l'issur everything except to protect it. And then
רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah comes and says, no, even things that are
like מלאכתו להיתר, melachto l'heter, I'm going to limit their use and
say only ממש mamash for their own purpose. Now again, in this
גמרא, Gemara רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah doesn't, it doesn't sound like רבי
נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah is being super restrictive. It sounds like all רבי
נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah is saying is, you have, you can't move it
to protect it from the sun. You can't move it maybe to
get it off the table, but it sounds like if you're using
the thing itself, you can use it for many different uses. But
based on other גמרות Gemaros and based on what it sounded like
in previous גמרות, Gemaros, רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah is interpreted even more
narrow, that even if you're using a מלאכתו להיתר, melachto l'heter. you
can only use it for its classic use. You cannot use anything
even, you know, you can't use a box for, I don't know,
for sitting on. You know, you can only use something for its
really classic use. Again, that doesn't come out in this discussion, but
it comes out in other discussions.
Yes, really, he has other discussions, I mean, I'm not...
Alright, you know, the other גמרא, Gemara like I said, either you
try to reconcile them and say that's what this גמרא Gemara means,
or you say that there are different סוגיות sugyos in the גמרא
Gemara about how to interpret רבי נחמיה. Rebbe Nechemiah. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, יתיב רב ספרא. yasiv Rav Safra.
Now we're going to go through, now that we have these things
laid out, it's going to be very much like there's a lot
of repeat the last two-three days because the same types of positions
are stated and then the same types of challenges are raised and
the same types of answers are given. So let's take a
look. יתיב רב ספרא ורב אחא בר הונא ורב הונא בר חיננא.
yasiv Rav Safra v'Rav Acha bar Huna v'Rav Huna bar Chinana. So
רב ספרא, Rav Safra, רב אחא Rav Acha the son of רב
הונא, Rav Huna, רב הונא Rav Huna the son of רב חנינא,
Rav Chanina, were sitting. ויתבי וקאמרי, v'yasvi v'ka'amri, they were sitting and
saying, לדרבה, l'Rabba, according to רבה, Rabba, who is the more restrictive
approach, אליבא דרבי נחמיה, aliba d'Rebbe Nechemiah, so רבה Rabba says that
even according to the rabbis you can only move, you can only
move כלי שמלאכתו להיתר, kli she'melachto l'heter, you can only move it
right for its own purpose or for the place. And comes along
רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah and says you can't even move it for
its place, you can only move it for its own purpose. So
according to that, if you can't move a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli
she'melachto l'heter just because you need its place, so אליבא דרבי נחמיה
הני קארי, aliba d'Rebbe Nechemiah hanei karei, the dishes on the table
after we're done eating, היכי מטלטלינן להו, heichi metalatlinan lehu, how do
we get them off the table? Okay, if you can't move anything
only for its own purpose, according to רבי נחמיה, Rebbe Nechemiah, you
can't even move things for its own place, how do you clear
the table? אמר להו רב ספרא, amar lehu Rav Safra, so רב
ספרא Rav Safra said, מידי דהוה אגרף של רעי, midi d'hava agraf
shel rei, and that's not a problem, same way you can like
remove a chamber pot, the special allowance to move מוקצה muktzah things
that are disgusting, so they allowed you to clear the table. אמר
ליה אביי לרבה, amar leh Abaye l'Rabba, so אביי Abaye said to
רבה, Rabba, למר, l'mar, according to the master, אליבא דרבי נחמיה, aliba
d'Rebbe Nechemiah, so that was a discussion not in the presence of
רבה. Rabba. That was a question of these rabbis including רב ספרא
Rav Safra that were speculating what רבה's Rabba position would be. So
now אביי, Abaye, a student of רבה, Rabba, asked רבה Rabba this
question directly. He said למר, l'mar, according to the master, אליבא דרבי
נחמיה הני קארי היכי מטלטלינן להו, aliba d'Rebbe Nechemiah hanei karei heichi
metalatlinan lehu, how would we clear the table according to רבי נחמיה
Rebbe Nechemiah if you cannot use, move a כלי kli even לצורך
מקומו? l'tzorech mekomo? אמר ליה רב ספרא, amar leh Rav Safra, so
רב ספרא Rav Safra said to him, maybe to אביי, Abaye, maybe
to רבה, Rabba, but anyway he reported this discussion that they had
just had on this topic. חברייא תרגמוה, chavraya targumah, so the colleagues
have explained this, מידי דהוה אגרף של רעי, midi d'hava agraf shel
rei, that the explanation is as that it's like the removal, so
he came to defend רבה Rabba about this discussion because they were
also speculating how רבה Rabba and this is the answer they came
up with. It's interesting because in the story it was רב ספרא
Rav Safra who came up with the answer. Now when he's reporting
the answer to רבה, Rabba, he's sort of attributing it to the
group. Oh, we were learning, this is the answer we came up
with, or the colleagues came up with. He wasn't taking personal credit
for it.
What? Maybe that's more important here that the opinion is more generally
accepted since it makes a lot of sense?
Maybe, maybe to say more people, maybe also it was more respectful,
rather than saying I have an answer to a question you can't
answer, he was sort of, you know, here's something that they were
thinking, we were thinking about in the ישיבה. yeshiva. Alright, anyway, so
that's the answer. Now, אתיביה אביי לרבה, esivei Abaye l'Rabba, so that's
a question about can רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah really be as restrictive
as he sounds? Now we're going to get to the broader question
about what is whether how, you know, what is the limits for
getting רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemiah that you can move various כלים, so
same types of questions we asked before. אתיביה אביי לרבה מדוכה, esivei
Abaye l'Rabba meducha, again, this mortar, אם יש בה שום, im yesh
bah shum, if it's got a... איתיביה ליה רבה. Aisivyei lei Rabba.
מדוכה, again this mortar, אם יש בה שום, im yeish bah shum,
if it's got the garlic, מטלטלין אותה, metaltelin osah, ואם לאו אין
מטלטלין אותה. v'im lav ein metaltelin osah. So you can only move
it with the garlic. So why is that? It's כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור.
kli shemelachto l'issur According to you, you should be allowed to move
it, right, whether it's גופו gufo or מקומו. mekomo. So הכא במאי
עסקינן מחמה לצל hacha be'mai asikin michama l'tzel that's not a problem.
I have one area you can't move it if you're doing it
to protect it. And that's what it means. איתיביה Aisivyei he challenged
him and ושווים v'shavim and I know
we'll get to that. ושווים שניכתה עליו בשר v'shavim she'nikitah alav basar
same questions that this type that this issue about the פסל pessal
which you know is this broad flat thing that you can use
ad hoc as a cutting board. So on יום טוב Yom Tov
בית שמאי ובית הלל Beis Shammai v'Beis Hillel let you use it
as a cutting board for the purpose of שמחת יום טוב. Simchas
Yom Tov. But after you've cut the meat on it שאסור לטלטלו
she'assur letaltelo you can't move it. Why not? Okay it's כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur but still you should be allowed to move
it. הכא במאי עסקינן מחמה לצל hacha be'mai asikin michama l'tzel same
answer. No it's talking about you're protecting it from the sun so
that one case you're not allowed to move it. והדתנן veha detnan
have it that which we taught אין סומכין את הקדירה בבקעת ein
somchin es hakedairah b'vikat you cannot support a pot again this is
on יום טוב Yom Tov with a like a log of wood.
Now a log of wood on יום טוב Yom Tov is not
מוקצה muktzah because you can make fire on יום טוב Yom Tov
and use it for your fire but you can't use this log
of wood to support a pot וכן בדלת v'chen b'delet and you
can't support a door with this log of wood. Why is that?
הא בקעת דיום טוב ha bikas d'Yom Tov דבר שמלאכתו להיתר הוא
davar shemelachto l'heter hu that's something that is a use for a
permissible use so and this is a question whether according to אביי
או רבא. Abaye o Rava. Here you're using something which is a
permissible use you're using it לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo why can't you
use it? Why can't you use this log of wood on יום
טוב? Yom Tov? It's מלאכתו להיתר. melachto l'heter אלמא דבר שמלאכתו להיתר
בין לצורך גופו בין לצורך מקומו אסור. alma davar shemelachto l'heter bein
l'tzorech gufo bein l'tzorech mekomo assur. It sounds like something that's מלאכתו
להיתר you can't use even for its own purpose. התם hasam so
you could have said רב נחמיה Rav Nechemya you could have said
קודם גזירת כלים kodem gizeiras keilim let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. התם מאי טעמא hasam mai ta'ama
here's the reason: כיון דבשבת דבר שמלאכתו לאיסור הוא keivan d'be'Shabbos davar
shemelachto l'issur hu
since on שבת Shabbos. a log of wood is מלאכתו לאיסור melachto
l'issur גזירה יום טוב אטו שבת. gizeirah Yom Tov atu Shabbos.
So therefore there's this interesting thing. Something that you can't use on
שבת Shabbos is כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur but on יום
טוב Yom Tov it's כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter right?
What is its status on יום טוב? Yom Tov? So here we're
saying that we're going to have to be consistent and apply if
it's מוקצה muktzah on שבת Shabbos or not מוקצה muktzah כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור kli shemelachto l'issur on שבת Shabbos it remains כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
kli shemelachto l'issur. on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now even if that's
true though who cares? So you're using it לצורך גופו l'tzorech gufo,
still why can't you use it? It should still be a problem.
I mean it still doesn't make sense. So the גמרא Gemara says
וכי תימא v'chi teima שבת גופה תשתרי Shabbos gufah tisharei
so even on שבת Shabbos a thing like that should be allowed
דדבר שמלאכתו לאיסור לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו שרי de'davar shemelachto l'issur l'tzorech
gufo l'tzorech mekomo shari
because something that's מלאכתו לאיסור melachto l'issur you can use לצורך גופו
l'tzorech gufo. מקומו. mekomo. So I still don't get it why should
it be a problem? So the גמרא Gemara says no הני מילי
היכא דאיכא תורת כלי עליו hani mili heicha d'ika toras kli alav
that's only when it's considered a כלי kli היכא דליכא תורת כלי
עליו
לא. heicha d'leika toras kli alav lo. If it's not a כלי
kli no and this is the point I've been mentioning to you
before that there's a profound difference. Our פרק perek is כל הכלים.
Kol HaKeilim. Once something is in the category of כלי kli. unless
it's like actively pushed away because it's like considered a מוקצה מחמת
מיאוס muktzah machmas mi'us or מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס muktzah machmas chisaron
kis but without those special circumstances anything that's a כלי kli. is
within your usable realm of objects. And at most it's a problem
of מלאכתו לאיסור melachto l'issur not moving it מחמה לצל. michama l'tzel.
But if something isn't a כלי kli. it's a log of wood
that's not a כלי. kli. Okay it's something you use but you
don't call it a vessel. It's not fashioned or whatever although it's
true some people do chop the wood to be a particular usable
but it's not considered a vessel and therefore it is fundamentally מוקצה.
muktzah. It's not כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto l'issur.
Even if you מייחד meiyached it before שבת?
Shabbos Well you can't if you מייחד meiyached on שבת Shabbos like
to sit on it then no but you can before שבת. Shabbos
You can't מייחד meiyached on שבת Shabbos for firewood. This was firewood
okay? So firewood on שבת Shabbat. is not כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli
shemelachto l'issur Firewood on שבת Shabbat, is מוקצה. muktzah. It's not a
כלי. kli So once it's מוקצה muktzah on שבת Shabbat? we treat
it also as מוקצה muktzah on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Now not
totally this is the irony because on יום טוב Yom Tov you
can use your firewood for firewood. So you just somehow can't use
it for anything other than firewood. So it becomes this very interesting
thing about how do we sort of level the שבת Shabbat? and
יום טוב Yom Tov but still allow you to use it on
יום טוב Yom Tov for things that it's legitimate to use it
for. But the point is is that we could that it's very
interesting. We cannot סתם stam say it's a יום טוב Yom Tov
problem because obviously you can use it on יום טוב Yom Tov
and once you can use it you can't call it מוקצה. muktzah.
And if you can't call it מוקצה muktzah you should be able
to use it for other things you should be able to use
it to support the support the pot and whatnot it's fundamentally not
מוקצה. muktzah. But on שבת Shabbat we can call it not only
a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto le'issur. because it's only a piece
of firewood we can even call it completely מוקצה. muktzah. And then
we allow to take that status and apply it to limit your
use on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Yes Charlie?
But I don't understand then how am I allowed to מייחד meiyached
my rock before שבת Shabbat as a paperweight? It's not a כלי.
kli No if you מייחד meiyached it's fine. So if you מייחד
meiyached this firewood to sit on it's fine but if you were
מייחד meiyached but this was firewood left aside for firewood so that
if that scenario on שבת Shabbat that doesn't make it a כלי.
kli Firewood for firewood is מוקצה muktzah okay? Again, it doesn't get
the status of כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto le'issur Somehow firewood, the
whole purpose of it being burned, you know, makes it considered—I guess
it's an interesting question. Let's say I designated this stick for, you
know, for a, for like a turning over something on a spit,
on a fire. So that might make it a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור
kli shemelachto le'issur. for שבת. Shabbat, Even though you can't do it
on שבת, Shabbat. it's still a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto l'issur
But designating it for firewood, firewood is not a כלי is my
point.
Okay? Now, what happens if people throw rocks on שבת? Shabbat. Are
you allowed to break stones on שבת? Shabbat? Okay, fine.
I'm not going to talk about that. Okay, moving on. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's our new—so now in
order to explain that, we introduced this idea that we're going to
take a מוקצה muktzeh status by שבת Shabbat and apply it to
יום טוב. Yom Tov. And now we're going to ask if that's
really true. So it says like this. גזירת יום טוב אטו שבת.
gezerat Yom Tov atu Shabbat. ומי גזרינן, u'mi gazrinan, do we really
apply a status of מוקצה muktzeh for שבת Shabbat. to יום טוב?
Yom Tov? והתנן. v'hatnan. Now this is going to be funny because
the examples it's going to give are general questions of equating שבת
Shabbos to יום טוב Yom Tov and not the same local issue
of a status of a particular status of מוקצה. muktzeh. We taught
in the משנה, משילין פירות דרך ארובה ביום טוב אבל לא בשבת.
mashilin perot derech aruba b'Yom Tov aval lo b'Shabbat.
You
can lower
down fruit from your sky—through your
skylight on יום טוב, Yom Tov, basically you have fruit drying out
on the roof and it's about to rain and get
ruined, or somewhere you're not expecting rain, so you can preserve it
on יום טוב Yom Tov by throwing it through the skylight, which
makes—which limits the amount of effort rather than like taking it down
in a more normal way. But on שבת, Shabbos we wouldn't even
allow that. So you see that we're not—we're not applying the similar
restrictions across the board. Now is that a—is that a מוקצה muktzeh
concern? Maybe it is מוקצה, muktzeh, stuff is drying on the roof.
Is it a טרחא tircha concern? But again, it's not like it
has a difference connected to the idea that you can cook on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? It's not similar to the firewood which
is linked to the idea of cooking. It's just like, okay, maybe
in one area we're more lenient on יום טוב Yom Tov than
שבת. Shabbos But that's at least the גמרא's Gemara point. You see
we're willing to make differences between יום טוב Yom Tov and שבת.
Shabbos So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי לא גזרינן? u'mi lo gazrinan?
What, do you think we don't? We don't equate יום טוב Yom
Tov and שבת? Shabbos והתנן, v'hatnan, we taught in the משנה, אין
בין יום טוב לשבת אלא אוכל נפש בלבד. ein bein Yom Tov
l'Shabbat ela ochel nefesh bilvad. The only difference is cooking, which means
that presumably for everything else that's not directly related to cooking, we
equate them, even for דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav
Yosef, לא קשיא. lo kashya. Here, I'm going to reconcile it, explain
why sometimes it sounds like we equate and sometimes we don't equate
for these דרבנן. d'rabbanan. הא רבי אליעזר הא רבי יהושע. ha Rabbi
Eliezer ha Rabbi Yehoshua. It's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and רבי יהושע that we saw earlier. דתניא, d'tanya, אותו ואת בנו
שנפלו לבור. oto v'et b'no she'naflu l'bor. An animal and its child
fell into the well.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, you can't shecht them both on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר, מעלה את הראשון
על מנת לשחטו ושוחטו. ma'aleh et harishon al menat lishchato v'shochto. You
can pull up the first one and you know, on the condition
that you're planning on shechting it, so then it's allowed for שמחת
יום טוב, simchat Yom Tov, and then you have to shecht it.
והשני, v'hasheni, and the second one, עושה לו פרנסה במקומו. oseh lo
parnasa bimkomo. You'd have to lower down food but you can't do
anything about it. It's not necessary for שמחת יום טוב. simchat Yom
Tov. We don't allow this טרחא. tircha. בשביל שלא ימות, bishvil shelo
yamut, so it doesn't die. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, מעלה
את הראשון על מנת לשחטו. ma'aleh et harishon al menat lishchato.
You can trick, you can say I'm taking up the first one
and I'm going to shecht it, ואינו שוחטו, v'eino shochto, then say,
you know what, I decided I don't want to shecht this one,
I want to shecht the other one. מערים, ma'arim, and you can
sort of scheme and trick, ומעלה את השני, u'ma'aleh et hasheni, and
bring up the second one saying, oh, that's the one I want
to shecht. And then when you get the second one up, you're
not committed to that one either. רצה זה שוחט רצה זה שוחט.
ratza zeh shochet ratza zeh shochet. Then you can change your mind
back to the first one. So he allows you to do a
whole trick to bring them both up. So what do you see?
So how's that relevant? So basically the גמרא Gemara wants to say
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. is more restrictive about what he lets
you do even on יום טוב Yom Tov לצורך יום טוב, letzorech
Yom Tov, and רבי יהושע is more lenient. So therefore the idea
that you could throw the fruit off the roof on יום טוב
Yom Tov would be the approach that is more lenient and lets
you for things that are צורך יום טוב tzorech Yom Tov and
הפסד hefsed and whatever. And the approach that we don't make any
difference is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer But then, you know, it's more
of a debate about יום טוב Yom Tov than a fundamental debate
about do we equate יום טוב Yom Tov to שבת Shabbos. or
not. But that's the point. If somebody basically has an attitude we're
going even scheme to allow you to—to you know, to give you
latitude on יום טוב, Yom Tov, then he would be willing to
make a distinction between יום טוב Yom Tov and שבת. Shabbos Yes.
What would be the problem of dropping fruits through a skylight?
It's basically either טרחא tircha as I said, it's just undue effort,
or מוקצה muktzeh if the fruits on the top are considered
מוקצה. muktzeh. Okay, same thing about raising an animal from the well.
Can you eat fruit? No, but if it's drying out and you
wanted it to stay there in order to finish the drying process.
Yes. Is מערים ma'arim fooling God?
Right. Right. Well, right.
You know, it's sort of like when we talk about—it's a general
category in הלכה halacha called הערמה, ha'arama, like when we sell our
פסח. You know, which means that when we sell our פסח, when
we sell our חמץ chametz ערב פסח. You know, it sort of
means that like—it means that you're sort of adhering to the letter
of the law but not the spirit. So the מערים ma'arim is
in terms, you—so but you're right.
I mean, it's basically taking them both.
Takes them both out but ostensibly— do it like if somebody were
to ask you why you're doing it, you would have to say
'cause I'm planning on שחיטה shechting it. You know, you can't say
I'm doing it to save it.
Exactly, and ספר החינוך Sefer HaChinuch doesn't mention...
well the גמרא Gemara actually before did say צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar
Ba'alei Chayim might have been the motive that well for the one
that says you're allowed to be מערים ma'arim that might have been
what was pushing him. Okay, now it is true that if there's
a צער בעלי חיים Tza'ar Ba'alei Chayim issue there are ways to
do it if you're if it's only a דרבנן d'rabbanan concern and
those are other גמרות. Gemaros. The גמרא Gemara will actually get to
a little bit later. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this ממאי who says that that's what it's about דילמא that it's
connected to this debate דילמא עד כאן לא קאמר רבי אליעזר התם
אלא דאפשר לפרנסה dilma ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer hatam ela
d'efshar l'farnesa maybe רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer only says that he's restrictive
because there's alternatives you can lower down food and there's not a
loss אבל היכא דלא אפשר לפרנסה aval heicha d'lo efshar l'farnesa when
you cannot sort of you know provide food meaning when you cannot
save yourself from a loss like the fruit that's going to get
ruined לא lo he would not be restrictive אינמי einami or עד
כאן לא קאמר רבי יהושע התם דאפשר בהערמה ad kan lo ka'amar
Rabbi Yehoshua hatam d'efshar b'ha'aramah maybe רבי יהושע is only is only
permissible because you can frame it in a permissible way oh I
you know you can do your trick אבל היכא דלא אפשר בהערמה
aval heicha d'lo efshar b'ha'aramah if you can't make it frame it
in a permissible way you have to directly override a prohibition so
לא lo, maybe he wouldn't allow it. So you can't say that
that debate can necessarily be applied elsewhere. אלא אמר רבא Ela amar
Rava רב פפא Rav Pappa לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult
that some things seem to equate יום טוב Yom Tov for שבת
Shabbos and some things do not. Again it's funny because it's not
all the same question of מוקצה muktzah or whatever but anyway it's
not difficult דתני בבית שמאי ובית הלל d'tani Beis Shammai v'Beis Hillel
debate of בית שמאי Beis Shammai בית הלל Beis Hillel דתנן בית
שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim and here it's really shocking that the
גמרא Gemara makes this comparison אין מוציאין
את הקטן ואת הלולב ואת ספר תורה לרשות הרבים. ein motzi'in es
hakatan v'es halulav v'es sefer Torah l'reshus harabbim. This is something that
we'll have a lot of fun with when we get to ביצה
Beitzah but there's the question about you know we discussed a minute
ago כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter on שבת Shabbos do you
need a reason to move it or is it completely מותר. muttar.
Well the same type of issue comes up about carrying on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. We basically think in our mind set that there's
no איסור issur carrying on יום טוב Yom Tov like there's no
איסור issur it's totally מותר muttar to carry. Actually that's questionable. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says that there is an איסור issur to carry
on יום טוב Yom Tov and you need a צורך tzorech to
allow it. Even בית הלל Beis Hillel might need a צורך tzorech
and maybe carrying for no purpose might not be allowed. So this
is we'll have fun talking about that when we get to ביצה
Beitzah but here's what בית שמאי Beis Shammai says. בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says you cannot take out the kid, you cannot take out
a לולב, lulav, ספר תורה Sefer Torah לרשות הרבים l'reshus harabbim meaning
even something that you would say is like a צורך מצוה tzorech
mitzvah you know maybe it only is something that's אוכל נפש ochel
nefesh maybe only something food related, very restrictive about carrying on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. בית הלל מתירים, Beis Hillel matirim, בית הלל Beis
Hillel allows it. Even בית הלל Beis Hillel maybe he needs a
צורך tzorech and so on. Anyway something we'll talk about. But anyway
so you see that here בית שמאי Beis Shammai is treats carrying
on יום טוב Yom Tov pretty similar to שבת Shabbos, and בית
הלל Beis Hillel does not. So you treat יום טוב Yom Tov
like שבת Shabbos maybe that's the debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Again because this isn't צורך אוכל נפש tzorech
ochel nefesh you're not eating, anyway eating everybody agrees is different, but
would you make differences in areas not eating. So בית שמאי Beis
Shammai pretty much tries to equate them as much as possible even
though it's a non-eating area and בית הלל Beis Hillel is willing
to keep a distinction. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute אימור
דשמעת ליה לבית שמאי eimur d'shamas lei l'Beis Shammai when did בית
שמאי Beis Shammai said we're going to be strict הוצאה, hotza'ah, that's
by carrying, that's a biblical concern. טלטול מי שמעת ליה tiltul mi
shamas lei who says that he's going to be strict by carrying
by מוקצה muktzah on יום טוב? Yom Tov? So just because you're
strict by carrying. So the גמרא Gemara says וטלטול גופיה לאו משום
הוצאה הוא v'tiltul gufeih lav mishum hotza'ah hu what isn't טלטול tiltul
itself because of הוצאה? hotza'ah? Now that's a very interesting fascinating line
of the גמרא Gemara which is one line that actually reveals what
a איסור issur where what the איסור מוקצה issur muktzah might be
about. If you look at רש"י Rashi he says sixth line line
טלטול לאו משום הוצאה הוא tiltul lav mishum hotza'ah hu בתמיה b'simyah
הלכך אם מזלזל בטלטול מזלזל בהוצאה hilkach im mezalzel b'tiltul mezalzel b'hotza'ah
if you are lenient about moving מוקצה muktzah you'll come to carry
which means and רש"י Rashi in ביצה Beitzah says it even more
clearly according to at least this גמרא Gemara the reason they forbade
מוקצה muktzah was because if they allowed you too much latitude about
moving things around then you know if you're moving everything then you
come to bring them outside. But if you're generally self-conscious about what
things are you touching and what not touching what things are you
moving you'll be more self-conscious about what things are you carrying with
you when you go outside. So that basically explains that the מוקצה
muktzah concern is a carrying concern. So some ראשונים Rishonim really say
this that's what all that's what all of מוקצה muktzah was based
on was a concern of carrying. As I said the other day
there are many other explanations in the ראשונים Rishonim for מוקצה. muktzah.
The most obvious one is the one in the beginning of the
גמרא Gemara in ביצה Beitzah about והכינו את אשר יביאו v'heichinu es
asher yavi'u the whole idea about being מכין mechin preparing things for
שבת Shabbos so even the vessels have to be prepared. So even
though you don't consciously say I'm going to use this this and
this but the things that you normally would use are considered as
if you prepared them. Things that normally wouldn't be in your mind
are not prepared for שבת. Shabbos That's an easy explanation for מוקצה.
muktzah. The רמב"ם'ס Rambam's explanation for מוקצה muktzah is that you don't
that for people that generally don't work during the during the weekday
you know the the independently wealthy you need something that makes שבת
Shabbos. different than the weekday. So therefore something that makes it a
little bit more restrictive. Small class of people? Well it's one of
the reasons he gives among others. Okay, in this גמרא Gemara. we
saw that they did it also to make שבת Shabbos different because
people were there was too much חילול שבת Chilul Shabbos going on.
So different things to sort of and this is quite funny, you
know, I do want to point out something about מוקצה. Muktzah. You
ask kids and kids מוקצה Muktzah so much dominates people's mindset about
what שבת Shabbat is for kids anything that's אסור assur on שבת,
Shabbat it's אסור assur because it's מוקצה. Muktzah. Right? You can't turn
on the light cause it's מוקצה. Muktzah. You can't what? You can't
cook cause it's מוקצה. Muktzah. Okay and it becomes מוקצה Muktzah basically
becomes now maybe because מוקצה Muktzah like don't move something creates a
sense of taboo, you know, creates a sense of like what?
Half the מסכתא... masechta...
well no, half the מסכתא masechta is about carrying but anyway so
it is interesting this idea that מוקצה Muktzah not only is it
cause of carrying again half the מסכתא masechta is about carrying and
the other and the other half of the other half is about
מוקצה. Muktzah. So now it's all about carrying but the idea that
מוקצה Muktzah also was a way of dealing or גזירת כלים gezeiras
keilim with rampant חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbos, that מוקצה Muktzah creates this
sense of like, you know, taboo and שבת Shabbos is different and
things are, you know, there's this more like sort of almost inviolate
nature in the air. It's interesting psychologically what מוקצה Muktzah does. But
here the גמרא Gemara at least connects it to carrying and it
says so בית שמאי Beis Shammai that's restrictive about carrying on יום
טוב Yom Tov would be restrictive about מוקצה. Muktzah. Now again the
question is presumably the reason they're restrictive about carrying has to deal
with דאורייתא De'Oraisa concerns of to what degree do you think that
the תורה Torah did or didn't allow carrying on יום טוב? Yom
Tov? But how that then translates into the דרבנן, DeRabbanan, but maybe
that's true, if you're more restrictive about if the they feel the
תורה Torah is more restrictive about carrying on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
then they feel we as the רבנים Rabbanim need to be more
restrictive about מוקצה Muktzah as well. But it is an interesting גמרא
Gemara that questions whether we take מוקצה Muktzah realities of שבת Shabbos
where the איסור issur is different than יום טוב Yom Tov and
apply those מוקצה Muktzah realities from שבת Shabbos to יום טוב. Yom
Tov. There's some question.
What was the רמב"ן Ramban's reason again?
רמב"ם. Rambam. He says this.
He quoted רמב"ן. Ramban. He said the first one. So the רמב"ם...
Rambam...
there's the reason I said. One is טלטול, tiltul, one is הוצאה,
hotza'ah, one is והכינו את אשר יביאו. V'heichinu es asher yavi'u.
Wasn't that just by food though?
Okay, but you know, to understand that then it becomes אינו מן
המוכן eino min hamuchan becomes a phrase used generally by מוקצה Muktzah
and could be understood to be, well, you're looking at the beginning
of ביצה. Beitzah. Yes, conceptually it's the same idea, preparing for שבת.
Shabbos? But the other idea, which I think actually is what works,
you know, what is true with a lot of people's mindset is
like the גמרא Gemara said about where גזירת כלים gezeiras keilim came
from, to create this sense of שבת Shabbos being different and off
limits. Okay. So now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara ואף רב
סבר לה להא דרבא. Ve'af Rav savar lah l'ha deRava. Even רב
Rav holds of רבא, Rava. the idea that we're back to the
general פסק הלכה psak halacha that כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto l'heter
is completely permissible and שמלאכתו לאיסור shemelachto l'issur is permissible לצורך מקומו.
l'tzorech mekomo. דאמר רב מר De'amar Rav, mar if you have a
מר mar which is I think like a hoe or a shovel,
שלא יגנב, shelo yiganev, you can, you know, that you want to
get it out of the... that you want to remove it, you
know, put it somewhere so it doesn't get stolen. זהו טלטול שלא
לצורך. zehu tiltul shelo l'tzorech. That's moving without a purpose, that's forbidden
ואסור, v'assur, it's forbidden. So what's that? A כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור מחמה
לצל. kli shemelachto l'issur mechama l'tzel. And that's the only thing that's
forbidden. טעמא שלא יגנב, Ta'ama shelo yiganev, the only issue is that
it shouldn't get stolen. אבל לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו, Aval l'tzorech gufo
ul'tzorech mekomo, if you wanted to move a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli
shemelachto l'issur. not only for its own purpose but just for to
get it off the table, מותר, mutar, that would be permissible. So
now we have רב Rav and רבא Rava saying it and that's
the way we פוסקן pasken it. אייתי דהא ראיה Aysei deha raya
from רב כהנא Rav Kahana איקלע לבי רב. ikla l'bei Rav. רב
כהנא Rav Kahana came to the house of רב Rav ואמר אייתו
ליה שוצא לכהנא v'amar aisu lei shutza l'Kahana and רב Rav said
to his like servants, he said, go bring a שוצא shutza which
is some type of a רש"י Rashi says like a net, some
type of a thing that's again a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto
le'issur Go bring it for כהנא Kahana that he can sit on
it,
ליתיב ליה. leiseiv lei. So why did he have to emphasize to
sit on it? לאו למימר, Lav l'meimar, wasn't he trying to underscore
the point? דדבר שמלאכתו לאיסור, D'davar shemelachto l'issur, yes it's something that's
מלאכתו לאיסור, melachto l'issur, but I'm telling you to move it לצורך
גופו אין l'tzorech gufo in because we're going to use it. But
לצורך מקומו l'tzorech mekomo presumably the subtext was that if you just
needed the space, לא, lo it would not have been allowed. So
who knows, you know, maybe he wasn't being so careful thinking everybody
was going to be מדייק medayek every little word that he said,
but the גמרא Gemara is being מדייק. medayek. So the גמרא Gemara.
says הכי אמר להו. hachi amar lehu. No, this is what he
said to
them. שקלו שוצא מקמי כהנא. Shiklu shutza mikamei Kahana. No, no, no.
Here, what he said was remove this net so that כהנא Kahana
can sit down. So he actually was switching it to be a
לצורך מקומו l'tzorech mekomo case. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima, if you want
you could say, התם מחמה לצל הוה. hasam mechama l'tzel hava. There
it was from מחמה לצל mechama l'tzel
and therefore and this is very important because this is like I
said, if you've got your hammer out in the yard and it's
about to rain, you better find some nuts you want to crack.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara basically says is that it was
out in the yard, it would have gotten it would have gotten
damaged and what he said, oh, move it לצורך גופו, he was
using the idea of underscoring we're doing it לצורך כהנא l'tzorech Kahana
as a way to make it permissible and it wouldn't be מחמה
לצל mechama l'tzel and that people should not confuse that the reason
he was moving it was because of מחמה לצל. mechama l'tzel. But
in the end, yes, you can also move it לצורך מקומו l'tzorech
mekomo not only לצורך גופו. Okay. רב מרי בר רחל הוה ליה
ההוא בי סדיותא. Rav Mari bar Rachel hava lei hahu bei sadyusa.
רב מרי בר רחל Rav Mari bar Rachel had a certain type
of
like
a
like a... a cushion
בשמשא bashimsho in the sun. אתא ata לקמיה דרבא, lakamei deRava, אמר
ליה amar lei מהו לטלטולי? mahu letiltulei? So this is a כלי
שמלאכתו להיתר. kli shemelachto leheter. He said can I get it out
of the sun? אמר ליה amar lei שרי, shari, it's permissible. He
said but wait חזיא אחרינא, chazya achrina, I don't need it, I
have another cushion I can use. So he says חזיא אורחין, chazya
orchin, he says big deal, so you bring it in for this
anyway, maybe you'll have guests. חזיא נמי לאורחין, chazya nami le'orchin, you
know what I have enough cushions even for my guests. Now he
was so he says if you didn't want my פסק psak why
you come to me? No! אמר ליה amar lei you can see
why you're complaining.
So he said to him so why is he why are you
resisting? גליא דעתך galya da'atach you are you are demonstrating that you
that your that you hold כרבא סבירא לך. kerava svira lach. You
hold like רבא. Rava You hold that even though it's כלי שמלאכתו
להיתר kli shemelachto leheter it's not permissible מחמה לצל. michama litzel. I
hold it is permissible מחמה לצל, michama litzel, you're holding like רבא
Rava that it's not. So לכולי עלמא שרי lechulei alma shari fine,
anybody else who asks me it's מותר, mutar, בדידי אסר, bedidi asar,
for you you want to say it's אסר, asar, for you it
can be אסר. asar. So okay. אמר
רבי אבא אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב amar Rabi Abba
amar Rabi Chiyya bar Ashi amar Rav so now he's in the
name of רב. Rav. מכבדות של מילתא machbadot shel milta if you
have basically brooms of like cloth of like rags which are basically
used for like you know squeeze it's like wiping off tables or
whatever, so it's כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto leheter מותר לטלטלן mutar
letiltalan and you can move them בשבת. אבל של תמרה aval shel
tmara if they're like of fronds which basically would be used for
sweeping the floor and you're not allowed to sweep the floors in
the גמרא because they were dirt floors and you'd be smoothing the
floor on שבת Shabbos. so that's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto
le'issur. לא you can't move it. Again to what degree you can't
move it but it's a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. kli shemelachto le'issur? ורבי
אליעזר אומר v'Rabi Eliezer omer אף של תמרה af shel tmara you
can even do the ones of the fronds. So the גמרא says
במאי עסקינן? bemai askinan? What are we talking about? Why do you
want to move this this broom that you're not that's כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור? kli shemelachto le'issur אילימא לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו eilima letzorech gufo
uletzorech mikomo if it's because you want to use it for a
permissible use or to get it out of the way, והאמר רב
אף של תמרה לא v'ha'amar Rav af shel tmara lo why would
רב Rav say you can't move it? והא רב כרבא סבירא ליה
v'ha Rav kerava svira lei we just got through saying that רב
Rav holds that a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto le'issur you can
move even לצורך מקומו letzorech mikomo even to get out of the
way סבירא ליה. svira lei. אלא מחמה לצל ela michama litzel but
rather oh we must say that if he's got a problem with
a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto le'issur it's because you're trying to
protect it from being damaged. So בהא לימא רבי אליעזר אף של
תמרה beha leima Rabi Eliezer af shel tmara so would רבי אליעזר
Rabi Eliezer say you could move it to protect it? Nobody says
you could use a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli shemelachto le'issur to protect.
So לעולם מחמה לצל le'olam michama litzel yes we're talking מחמה לצל
michama litzel that's why רב Rav says it's forbidden because that's the
only case that רב Rav would say it's forbidden. And so what
do we do with רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer that said it's permissible?
אימא וכן אמר רבי אליעזר eima vechen amar Rabi Eliezer rather than
having רבי אליעזר arguing and say it's forbidden have him say and
he agreed that it is also... eima rather have him arguing and
say it's permissible switch the גרסא girsa and have him agree and
say that it is forbidden. So again this sounds like we had
to rearrange this because it sounded like רב Rav was more restrictive
and we have we basically have have said that רב Rav holds
like רבא Rava the more lenient position that even a כלי שמלאכתו
לאיסור kli shemelachto le'issur you can move לצורך גופו ולצורך מקומו letzorech
gufo uletzorech mikomo and that basically is how we rule. So basically
a כלי שמלאכתו להיתר kli shemelachto leheter you can move for any
purpose. There was a certain issue that came up earlier about can
you move it for no purpose. And a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור you
can move if you need to use it if you need its
space but the one thing you can't move it for is if
you need to protect it. Yes.
Wouldn't it be more correct to say that רבא Rava holds like
רב Rav because רב Rav was earlier?
Yes that's actually very correct but since we had introduced רבא already
for the last דף daf and a half we said רב Rav
holds like רבא but you're correct רב Rav is definitely the earlier
position. Of course this whole thing about moving the broom and people
coming in and moving it you know reminds you you know that
famous story about the rabbi that didn't want his students you know
was afraid that every student would and be מדייק medayek every word
that the rabbi said to what he holds, you know the rabbi
what they I forget who they say it with you know they
they the rabbi was coming to light חנוכה Chanukah candles and there
was a broom in the room. He didn't think it was כבוד
kavod but he knew his students were so crazy that if he
that if he like you know removed the broom they would think
it's אסור assur to have a broom in the room. So when
light חנוכה Chanukah candles so he goes and he whispers to his
wife to like take the broom out before light. So his wife
takes the broom out. So ever since that year all of his
תלמידים talmidim make sure to put a broom in the room when
they're lighting חנוכה Chanukah candles and tell their wives to move the
broom. Anyway so something like that. Anyway you want a different version?
נשתקעו הדברים. nishtakeu hadvarim. What oh נשתקעו הדברים nishtakeu hadvarim so then
they always do it as they say נשתקעו הדברים. nishtakeu hadvarim. Okay
that's a good version of it too. Okay let's get a little
bit further. כל הכלים הניטלין בשבת kol hakelim hanitlin b'Shabbat so שבריהן
ניטלין עמהן. shivreihen nitlin imahen. So the first משנה talked about if
their doors fell off. Here talks about if they break. The vessel
breaks you can even use you can even move the broken parts
of the vessel. ובלבד שהן עושין מעין מלאכה uvilvad shehen osin me'ein
melacha as long as they can still the broken parts can still
be used to do some type of this does not mean the
מלאכה melacha in the שבת Shabbos sense can be used for some
type of a function. שברי
עריבה shivrei areiva let's say you have a kneading trough that broke
that broke לכסות בהן את פי החבית lechasot bahen et pi hachavit
as long as you can use a piece of it to cover
like a barrel. so then you can move that piece it has
some function. שיורי זכוכית Shiurei zechuchis you have glass that broke, לחסות
בה את פי הפך lachzos bo es pi hapach so as long
as you can use a piece of it I don't know what
you're doing handling broken glass but anyway some type of a small
little like perfume bottle. Okay you can make some use. רבי יהודה
אומר בלבד שהיו עושים מעין מלאכתן. bilvad shehu osin me'ein melachtan.
In order for them not to be מוקצה muktzah they have to
be able to do similar to their original function. Right well yeah
but this but this is a different concern.
שיורי עריבה Shiurei areiva לצוק לתוכן מקצה letzoke letochan miktze if you
have the broken kneading trough it has to be enough of a
piece that you can put a little porridge into it so it
still holds like something and it holds something similar to like dough.
ושל זכוכית V'shel zechuchis and something like glass לצוק לתוכה שמן letzoke
letocha shemen it has to be able to at least have a
curvature and to hold some oil in it again the same way
your whole glass bottle was used for holding liquids. Okay let's just
read a little of the גמרא. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel מחלוקת שנשברו מערב שבת. machlokes shenishberu me'erev Shabbos.
The case is that these vessels broke ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. מר
סבר מעין מלאכתן אין מעין מלאכה אחרת לא Mar savar me'ein melachtan
in me'ein melacha acheres lo
that one says only that one holds only if it can do
some of the original function it's still a vessel ומר סבר אפילו
מעין מלאכה אחרת u'mar savar afilu me'ein melacha acheres even if it
can do any function it's a vessel it's a new type of
a vessel it's a pot cover or whatever it is you know
or barrel cover. אבל נשברו בשבת Aval nishberu b'Shabbos
if it broke on שבת Shabbos דברי הכל מותרין divrei hakol mutarin
that makes it easier because everybody would say it's מותר mutar as
long as it has some function הואיל ומוכנים אגב אביהן ho'il u'muchanim
agav avihen since when שבת Shabbos? began it was not מוקצה muktzah
it retains the מותר mutar status more easily. So it's a bigger
it's harder if it breaks ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. If it broke
on שבת Shabbos then the permissible status is you know more adheres
to it it doesn't go off so well so easy. That's what
he says. Now we're going to have the opposite approach. מתיב רב
זוטרא Meseiv Rav Zutra one minute he asks we teach מסיקין בכלים
ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים. masikin bechalim v'ein masikin beshivrei chelim. On יום
טוב Yom Tov you can throw vessels into the fire but not
broken parts of a vessel. So what type when did they break?
דנשברו אימת? Denishberu eimas? When did these broken vessels break that you
can't use them for firewood? אילימא דנשברו מערב יום טוב? Ilima denishberu
me'erev Yom Tov?
If they broke before יום טוב Yom Tov עצים בעלמא הוו eitzim
b'alma havu so of course you should be able if they're broken
stuff it's firewood why shouldn't you be able to use it on
יום טוב? Yom Tov? אלא לאו בשבת? Ela lav b'Shabbos? It broke
on שבת? Shabbos וקתני מסיקין בכלים ואין מסיקין בשברי כלים. vekatani masikin
bechalim v'ein masikin beshivrei chelim.
And nevertheless it says you can't use the broken vessels for firewood.
Why? You said if it starts שבת Shabbos. or presumably יום טוב
Yom Tov as מותר mutar as not מוקצה muktzah then even after
it breaks it remains okay as long as it has some use.
So this vessel should remain totally okay the broken pieces use it
as firewood and you can't. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר Ela i
itmar hachi itmar or it said it was the exact opposite of
what of what the earlier version. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar
Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel מחלוקת שנשברו בשבת. machlokes shenishberu b'Shabbos.
The issue is they broke on שבת. Shabbos On שבת Shabbos doesn't
make it better it makes it worse. Why? Because if it changed
on שבת Shabbos what problem would you have if something changed its
status on שבת? Change its state? נולד. Nolad. So one argument is
it's better because it started מותר mutar when שבת began and that
state should retain. But here the argument is the opposite. No it's
something new came into the world. דמר סבר מוכן הוא Demar savar
muchan hu
it's still considered prepared like the same way it was okay when
שבת began it remains okay and as long as it can still
do some function it's not נולד. nolad. ומר סבר נולד הוא U'mar
savar nolad hu and the other says look if it can do
part of the original function now you understand why it needs to
do the original function if it can do part of the original
function it's like the same vessel it's not נולד. nolad. But if
it can only do a different function then it's נולד. nolad. That's
if it breaks
on שבת. אבל מערב שבת Aval me'erev Shabbos if it broke
ערב שבת erev Shabbos דברי הכל מותרין divrei hakol mutarin everybody would
say it's permissible just like the thing that broke could be used
for firewood הואיל והוכנו למלאכה מבעוד יום ho'il v'huchnu lemelacha miba'od yom
since it actually could be
it's not נולד nolad and it had some function when שבת began.
Now of course the question is what's the context? If it broke
and you threw it in the garbage then it doesn't matter that
it had some function but presumably it means it broke and you
were still somehow planning on using it. So this way ערב שבת
erev Shabbos so this is the question. Is it better on שבת
because the status of מותר mutar maybe retained more? Or what the
גמרא is now saying is it's worse if it breaks on שבת
because it's a נולד nolad issue? But if it breaks on ערב
שבת erev Shabbos then maybe we would argue if it could have
still some use then it could retain then it could start as
considered to be a כלי even though it's a broken כלי and
we'll continue with more of this tomorrow.